□ nikos.daniilidis@gmail.com 1 http://nikosd.me in ndaniilidis nikos-daniilidis

Nikos Daniilidis

Profile

Scientist committed to extracting insights from data-intensive applications.

Background: Atomic physics; condensed matter physics; electrical & computer engineering

Expertise: Scientific programming & data analysis; modeling & characterization; computer-

aided control & optimization; scientific writing

Team worker: Worked with large teams building complex experimental setups

Presenter: 10+ years experience presenting at conferences & funding-review meetings

Supervisor: Guided graduate and undergraduate students in their projects

Manager: Co-authored research grants, helped plan & set up UC Berkeley ion trapping lab

Education

2007 PhD, Physics, Brown University, X. S. Ling group.

Statistical data analysis: regression analysis, hypothesis testing, data analysis pipeline development (Matlab)

2003 **MSc, Physics**, *Brown University*.

Statistical physics, ODEs, PDEs, Complex Analysis

2001 Diploma, Electrical & Computer Engineering, National Technical University of

Athens, (5 year degree, Bachelor's & MSc combined).

Algorithms & Data Structures (C), Numerical Analysis (FORTRAN), Signal Processing, Probability, Statistics

Professional Experience

2009–2014 **Post Doc**, *University of California, Berkeley*, H. Häffner group.

Designed, analyzed experiments, built ion-trap analysis & control toolbox (Matlab), coauthored grants.

2007-2009 Post Doc, Institute for Quantum Optics and Quantum Information, Austria.

> Designed, analyzed experiments, built data analysis pipeline (Matlab, Python), built/tested ion trap electrostatic solver pipeline (Ansoft Maxwell, Simion CPO, Matlab).

2007–2008 **Post Doc**, ETH Zürich, Zurich, Switzerland, A. Wallraff group.

Fabricated the first 'made in Europe' ion trap microchips.

Programming Skills

Scientific Python (proficient), Matlab (proficient), R (intermediate), Scala (basic), SQL programming (intermediate)

DFS Hadoop/MapReduce (intermediate), Spark (basic)

Data Munging XML, HTML, JSON, PDF, text, floating point streams, binary streams & Analysis

General Skills

Scientific Grant proposals, scientific commentaries, research articles, review articles writing

Design & Experiment design, statistical analysis, modeling & characterization of noise pro-

Modeling cesses, electromagnetic simulations

Prototyping RF & digital electronics, microfabrication, lasers, vacuum, cryogenics

Professional Achievements

- Co-authored grants, worth in excess of \$1M (UCB);
- Participated in planning/building UC Berkeley ion trapping group (UCB);
- Coauthored fourteen publications (UCB, IQOQI, ETH, Brown, see http://nikosd.me/publications);
- Developed methods/algorithms/Matlab library for ion-trap electrostatic control (https://github.com/HaeffnerLab/trap-simulation-tools-matlab);
- Designed/Conducted/Analyzed data-intensive experiments (data analysis pipeline in Matlab, Python): ion trap (UCB, IQOQI, ETH), neutron scattering (Brown), ultrasonics (Brown);
- Built world's first ion trapping UHV system with in-situ surface analysis (UCB);

Resources

Projects http://nikosd.me/projects

Github https://github.com/nikos-daniilidis

Blog http://nikosd.me/

— Awards

2008–2010 Marie Curie Intra European Fellowship for Career Development, *European Commission*

2007 Forrest Award for Excellent Work Related to Experimental Apparatus, *Brown University*

2002 Award for Excellence as a Graduate Teaching Assistant, Brown University